Garson Kanin Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Garson Kanin Papers 1941-1965
MSS29280
Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999
2,500 items
18 containers
7.5 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Actor, author, producer, and director. Correspondence and production material relating to Kanin's stage and film projects.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Clair, René, 1898-1981--Correspondence.; Guinness, Alec, 1914-2000--Correspondence.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Amazing Adele. 1950.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Born yesterday. 1946.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Boy. 1956.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Come on strong. 1962.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Diary of Anne Frank. 1955.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Do re mi. 1955.; Kanin, Garson, 1912-1999. Hole in the head. 1956.; Massey, Dorothy Ludington, 1902-1982--Correspondence.; Sherwood, Robert E. (Robert Emmet), 1896-1955--Correspondence.
Subjects
Drama--Stories, plots, etc.; Motion pictures--Production and direction.; Theater--Production and direction.
Occupations
Actors.; Authors.; Motion picture directors.; Theatrical directors.
Provenance
The papers of Garson Kanin, actor, author, producer, and director, were deposited in the Library of Congress by Kanin in 1969.
Related Material
The Garson Kanin Papers complement the Ruth Gordon Papers and the Ruth Gordon and Garson Kanin Papers, which are also located in the Manuscript Division.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Garson Kanin are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1912, Nov. 24 Born, Rochester, N.Y.
1933 Graduated, American Academy of Dramatic Arts, New York, N.Y. Acted for the first time on Broadway in Little Ol' Boy
1934 Appeared in Spring Song (play)
1935 Appeared in Three Men on a Horse (play)
1936 Directed Hitch Your Wagon (play)
1938 Directed A Man to Remember (film)
1939 Directed The Great Man Votes (film)
1940 Directed My Favorite Wife (film)
1941 Directed Tom, Dick and Harry (film)
1941 1945 Served with the United States army
1942 Married Ruth Gordon (died 1985)
1945 Codirectored with Carol Reed, The True Glory, Dwight D. Eisenhower's film report on the Allied victory in Europe
1946 Wrote and directed Born Yesterday (play) for which he received the Donaldson Award and the Sidney Howard Memorial Award Directed Years Ago (play)
1948 Coauthored with Ruth Gordon A Double Life (screenplay)
1949 Coauthored with Ruth Gordon Adam's Rib (screenplay)
1950 Wrote the English libretto and directed Die Fledermaus for the Metropolitan Opera Co.
1952 Coauthored with Ruth Gordon Pat and Mike (screenplay)
1955 Wrote and directed The Diary of Anne Frank (play)
1959 Published Blow Up a Storm. New York: Random House
1960 Wrote and directed Do Re Mi (play)
1964 Directed Funny Girl (play)
1966 Published Remembering Mr. Maugham. New York: Atheneum
1969 Published Cast of Characters. New York: Atheneum
1971 Published Tracy and Hepburn: An Intimate Memoir. New York: Viking Press
1990 Married Marian Seldes
1999, Mar.13 Died, New York, N.Y.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Garson Kanin (1912-1999) span the years 1941-1965 and consist of General Correspondence and a Production File.
The General Correspondence features letters exchanged with the playwright, editor, and biographer Robert E. Sherwood beginning when Kanin was a private in military training in 1941 and ending with Sherwood's death in 1955. Other correspondents include René Clair, Alec Guinness, and Dorothy Massey.
The Production File is comprised of scripts of plays and screenplays that Kanin wrote or directed including The Amazing Adele, Born Yesterday, The Boy, Come On Strong, The Diary of Anne Frank, Do Re Mi, and A Hole in the Head. The scripts are accompanied by related matter such as casting deliberations, performance evaluations, technical notes, financial records, foreign productions, stock and amateur rights, publicity, and printed matter.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in two serines:
General Correspondence, 1941-1964
Production File, 1945-1965
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1941-1964 (Box 1)
  Letters sent and received by Kanin.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Clair, René See Container 5, Foreign productions, France (Box 1)
  - Guinness, Alec, 1964
  - Massey, Dorothy, undated
  - Sherwood, Madeline (Mrs. Robert E. Sherwood), 1949-1954
  - Sherwood, Robert E., 1941-1955, (4 folders)
- Production File, 1945-1965 (Box 1-18)
  Article, book, film, and stage files.
  Arranged by type of writing or production and therein alphabetically by title.
  - Article, “On Playwriting,” Diners' Club Magazine, 1962 (Box 1)
  - Book, Blow up a Storm, reviews, 1959-1960
  - Films
    - Born Yesterday
      - Script, 1950
      - Correspondence
        - Cohn, Harry, 1950-1951
        - Cukor, George, 1950
        - Frankfurter, Felix, undated
        - “H-W” miscellaneous, 1948-1956
      - Legal papers, 1947-1953
      - Miscellany, 1950
      - Printed matter, 1950-1951
    - The Old Boy, screenplay, 1956
    - The True Glory, printed matter, 1945
  - Stage (Box 2)
    - The Amazing Adele
      - Script, undated, (2 folders)
      - Correspondence, 1950
        - Barillet, Pierre
        - De Courville, Albert
        - Shubert, Lee
        - “A-W” miscellaneous
      - Financial records, 1950
      - Ticket requests, 1950, (5 folders)
      - Miscellany, 1950
      - Printed matter, 1950 (Box 3)
    - Born Yesterday
      - Script, 1945, (4 folders)
      - Books
        - Netherlands, undated
        - United States, 1946
      - Correspondence
        - Arthur, Jean, 1945
        - “A-B” miscellaneous, 1946-1951, 1963, (2 folders)
        - Chaney, Lon (1906-1973), 1948
        - “C-F” miscellaneous, 1946-1955, 1962, (3 folders) (Box 4)
        - Gordon, Max, 1945-1949
        - “G-L” miscellaneous, 1946-1951, (5 folders)
        - McKay, Scott, undated
        - Mantle, Burns, 1946
        - “M-O” miscellaneous, 1946-1949, (3 folders)
        - Pardoll, David, 1948-1949
        - Parker, Jean, 1948
        - Porter, Cole, 1948
        - “P” miscellaneous, 1946
        - Robinson, Edward G., 1949
        - Rogers, Ginger, 1949
        - “R-V” miscellaneous, 1946-1950, (5 folders)
        - William Morris Agency, 1946-1955
      - Foreign productions
        - Argentina, 1946-1953
        - Australia, 1948-1953
        - Austria, 1948-1950
        - Belgium, 1952-1958
        - Brazil, 1952-1954
        - China, 1948
        - Czechoslovakia, 1946-1951
        - Denmark, 1947-1960, (2 folders)
        - England, 1946-1959 (Box 5)
        - France, 1946-1949
        - Germany, 1947-1962
        - Greece, 1947-1948, 1957
        - Hungary, 1948
        - Iceland, 1951-1956
        - India, 1953-1959
        - Ireland, 1948-1949
        - Israel, 1948-1949
        - Italy, 1947-1953
        - Japan, 1949
        - Mexico, 1952-1959
        - Netherlands, 1947, 1958-1960
        - Norway, 1947-1956
        - Poland, 1946
        - Portugal, 1958
        - Spain, 1953-1959
        - Sweden, 1946-1959, (3 folders) (Box 6)
        - Switzerland, 1947
        - Turkey, 1959
        - Yugoslavia, 1959
      - Productions outside the continental United States
        - Hawaii, 1948-1949
        - Puerto Rico, 1962
      - Stage manager's reports
        - 1946, (4 folders)
        - 1947, (7 folders) (Box 7)
        - 1948, (5 folders) (Box 8)
        - 1949, (2 folders); (4 folders) (Box 9)
      - Financial papers, 1946-1951, (4 folders); (1 folder) (Box 10)
      - Stock and amateur rights, 1946-1959
      - Miscellany, 1949, undated
      - Printed matter, 1946-1950, 1966, undated, (2 folders)
    - The Boy, script, 1956 See also Containers 16-18, A Hole in the Head, (5 folders); (2 folders) (Box 11)
    - Come on Strong
      - Script, French translation, 1964
      - Correspondence
        - Bacall, Lauren, 1961
        - Baker, Carroll, 1961-1962
        - Cassini, Oleg, 1962
        - Davis, Sammy, 1962
        - Hopper, Hedda, 1962
        - Horne, Lena, 1962
        - Johnson, Van, 1961-1962
        - Merrick, David, 1962
        - Pardoll, David, 1962-1964
        - Stevens, Roger L., 1962
        - “A-W” miscellaneous, 1962-1965, (2 folders)
      - Casting, 1961-1962
      - Contracts, 1962-1963
      - Financial papers, 1962
      - Music, 1962
      - Production notes, 1961-1962, undated, (1 folder) (Box 12)
      - Stage manager's reports, 1962
      - Ticket requests for premiere, 1962
      - Printed matter, 1961-1962
    - The Diary of Anne Frank, scripts, undated, (4 folders) (Box 13)
    - Do Re Mi
      - Scripts, 1953-1961, undated, (3 folders); (7 folders); (8 folders); (1 folder) (Box 14, Box 15, Box 16)
      - Playbill, 1960
      - A Hole in the Head, Scripts, 1955-1957, undated See also Containers 10-11, The Boy, (5 folders); (8 folders); (2 folders) (Box 17, Box 18)
    - How I Wonder, contracts, 1947
    - The Rugged Path, printed matter, 1945